All right, we're excited now to be
joined by Field Gates from ESPN to break
down the Patriots off seasonason here. A
little bit of free agency, a little bit
of look forward to draft. Field, thanks
for taking the time here to hop on with
me.
>> No problem, Duce. Glad to be with you
today.
>> So, let's just start off with free
agency. You know, the Patriots um seem
like a lot of one forone moves, you
know, digs out, dos in, etc. Uh just
what were your impressions here of the
Patriots moves through the early part of
free agency?
>> Yeah, well said. And you can take it a
step further with moves like Draymond
Jones in, Caleb, Chaon out. They play a
different style of game, but still guys
that you expect to be or in the case of
Chaon was a starter, a very solid
starter for them at that. He was
especially great down the stretch and in
the playoffs. Draymond Jones, you expect
to be a starting edge rusher for this
franchise as well based off the
familiarity, the skill set, and also the
money, which is always a good thing to
follow during free agency. So, it feels
like an off season that um I feel like
there's more to be done. And that what I
mean by that is it feels like the
Patriots still have some cards left to
play. And that's not just the draft.
It's other ways other levers to pull uh
to continue to improve this roster.
Obviously, it's in very good shape. They
made the Super Bowl this past season,
but there are a couple of items on the
to-do list that I think this team is
going to still look to address.
>> Well, one of those items, could it be AJ
Brown? I mean, there's just so much
talk. I mean, Patriots fans have been
talking about AJ Brown forever.
>> We've been doing this dance for a couple
years now. It feels now they're saying
maybe after June 1st. What are your
thoughts on that whole potential coming
to fruition finally, AJ Brown to the
Patriots, is it real? Yeah, I think
where I've landed with AJ Brown is that
until either he comes out himself and
publicly commits to wanting to be a
Philadelphia Eagle for 2026 and beyond
or until we get to the start of the
regular season, I'm going to believe
there's a real possibility that he has
traded. There's just been so much
speculation and so much smoke and from
some of the top insiders in the game. My
colleague Adam Shester has been talking
about the possibility of an AJ Brown
trade and certainly made it seem like
that is still in play and he's
referencing that the Patriots are one of
the teams that still are a logical
landing spot perhaps at least in my
estimation the most logical landing spot
for AJ after June 1st and I think
probably most viewers and listeners to
this program already know this but after
June 1st it becomes a lot more palatable
from a salary cap standpoint for
Philadelphia to trade away AJ Brown. So
that's a long time to have to wait.
Still two and a half more months from
when you and I are talking right now.
But for a player of this caliber and for
a deal that would most likely involve
draft capital, you can wait until June
2nd to have a guy that would immediately
give the Patriots their best offensive
weapon for Drake May to distribute the
football to.
>> Just one more question for you, Phil,
about the offense. I just I felt like
this was a real Josh McDaniels kind of
offense. You know, we see Reggie Gilliam
come over from the Bills. Josh got to
have his fullback. You know, you take a
little bit of a chance on on Vera Tucker
who's had some injuries but has a high
upside. Uh it seems to me, you know, you
got to get a blocking tight end there
from Miami as well. Seems like they
really are focused on maybe building the
toughness, the physicality, short
yardage was an issue for them last year.
Uh and then you also bring in Dobs. How
do you see that all coming together?
>> Yeah, totally agree. Especially on those
first three players that you referenced,
kind of the identity of what they bring
to the table. Reggie Gilliam,
hard-nosed, excellent fullback, also
great on special teams. He'll help in
that regard. Julian Hill, a name that I
don't know how many people knew a whole
lot about Julian Hill. He's got a very
interesting background prior to playing
in the NFL, but to your point, he is
going to help the running game as well,
played in that very unique scheme in
Miami where he was on the move a lot and
carving out some paths for guys like
Devon Achan who of course was excellent
for Miami these past couple of seasons.
Um, but short yardage has to be better.
Uh, you know, there's always this push
pull when you've got a quarterback like
Drake May who can run the tush push and
assume that stays in 2026 and beyond,
but also a quarterback that you want to
protect. And then beyond that, you've
got a player in Trayvon Henderson who we
know how electric Trayvon is. He was
unbelievable for stretches last season,
but his role decreased down the stretch
and into the playoffs. He feels like the
kind of guy that's at his best running
between the tackles with somebody
leading the way for him. He's just not
going to be this gigantic power back and
Raandre was great last season,
especially down the stretch. It was kind
of the reverse of how Trayvon's impact
played out. But I think that both of
those guys will benefit from having a
hammered head in front of them. Jack
Westover gave them good snaps last
season. Jack much more of an angular
blocker, the kind of guy that's a factor
in the passing. Well, at least he was
during college, a factor in the passing
game, but not the kind of fullback that
we have seen for a lot of years for the
Patriots with Josh McDaniels. Most
recent versions include the likes of
YaKob Johnson and maybe Reggie Gilliam
can give you a bit more of what Yak gave
you for those years in New England.
>> Oh, I love the Yak shout out, of course.
Love our German Yakob Johnson. But, uh,
let's get let's get in the draft a
little bit at field and this is, you
know, weird. We're last couple years
you're talking top five picks and it's
going to be one of two or three guys.
Now we're back to picking at the bottom
of the first round where, you know, I
always like that spot a little bit
because maybe something gets pushed down
that you weren't really expecting. Maybe
it's not a huge need, but there's a very
talented player. A lot of talk about
this edge class. It's still a huge need
for the Patriots. Every time I look at a
mock draft, I get down to that 31st
spot. Who's the edge? You know, it's
it's either somebody has to slip through
the cracks or maybe you're reaching a
little bit. Just what are your general
thoughts down there at 31st overall here
in this draft? Well, there's two ways in
which this is trickier to forecast for
the Patriots than the past couple of
years where it was pick three and then
pick four. And that third pick two years
ago was especially easy when it was
going to be a quarterback and there were
three outstanding prospects at the top
and you just take whoever is left over
and I think the Patriots are thrilled
that Drake May is the guy they got. I
think frankly all three teams are
thrilled with how it played out, but
that's a different conversation for a
different appearance here on the show.
Um, this year it's more difficult, not
just because of the fact that there are
infinite scenarios that could take place
between 1 and 30, the 30 picks that
precede the Patriots, but also it's this
very unique draft class. It's a draft
class that's I would say breath the blue
chip talent. There are a few guys, but
not a lot of real difference makers. And
what you find, and earlier today, I
dropped my top 50 on ESPN.com, and I try
to be judicious and in checking comments
uh on social media when you do things
like that. However, I'd imagine there
are probably some people that are
frustrated about certain players being
too low, maybe a couple of players being
uh eyebrow raising in terms of how high
they are, but this is that draft class.
This is very much a choose your own
adventure draft class. I don't think
there's tons in the way of consensus. So
for the Patriots at 31, I think the
needs to me would stack up in some order
of continue to add add rushers. A wide
receiver with the caveat that if an AJ
Brown trade might get done after June
1st, it's not quite as pressing of a
need. I think a number two tight end or
number three tight end, I don't however
you want to categorize it, a guy that
can give you a little bit more than what
we have seen so far from Julian Hill as
a pass catcher. Uh with Hunter Henry
going into the final year of his current
contract. Uh those are some of the
positions that come to mind for me. Uh
and then continuing of course to hammer
along the offensive line. I think they
have their five guys if they were to
play a game tomorrow. Um but I al you
know they have a chance to have their
five guys if they play a game tomorrow.
I certainly think you know the AVT
signing gives them some real versatility
and upside when he is healthy. Uh but
they need to continue to add depth there
as we saw during the playoff and you
face off against the best pass rushers,
pass rushers and pass rushes as a group.
Uh you got to have not just five guys
you can really count on but a great
protection plan and also some depth.
>> Love what you're saying about the edge
and the tight end groups. I mean those
are two position groups at the combine.
We heard Vable Elliot Wolf both mention
those. I mean the tight ends totally
hear what you're saying. Like I just
they get younger, get a young one of
these athletic guys. Matt Cla from Ohio
State, one that I like. But want to talk
about two other positions down there,
though. And you had Caleb Lomu from Utah
as a tackle, uh, taken in 31st overall
in your first mock draft, which, you
know, to me, I think that's a need, too.
I'd also look at the safety position.
You know, does one of those guys get
pushed down a little bit. They just
signed Kevin B. He's on a one-year deal.
He's still playing at a high level.
You've got Craig Woodson kind of locked
in, but that could be a long position of
need. Are tackle and safety maybe two
darkhorse positions down there at 31st
overall that you could see them
consider?
I try to remind consumers of my content
this all the time is that like other
than quarterback, everything's kind of a
need for the Patriots because the NFL is
a unpredictable and there's a salary
cap. So players that are currently
fixtures may not be fixtures for the
next five or six years. So I think that
offensive line just in general talked
about a need. Safety could be a need as
well. Well, and I think that what we
realize with safeties, and this is
something that has really shifted over
the past couple of years, is that
there's a specific type of safety that a
Mike Vrabel and Zakur and Terrell
Williams defense is going to prioritize
and value. Right? There were guys who
just a couple of years ago looked like
they were going to be fixtures for the
Patriots and Kyle Duggar and also the
Bro Peppers and then both of them are
gone. Obviously, the Jaylen Hawkins for
Kevin Bard swap is one that brings tons
of familiarity. It's also a one-year
deal for a safety in his 30s as Kevin
Byer. So, if you could find a guy that
provides some of that ability to chop
off explosive plays down the field like
Bayern does, he's got premier ball
skills. He led the NFL interceptions
once again last season did Bard, but
safety is probably a bigger need than
maybe is currently being forecasted. Uh,
and the Patriots showed last year that
you can get some good players in the
middle rounds of the draft. Craig
Woodson was just excellent for them and
a guy that was it 102nd overall I think
it was for Craig. So not quite in the
middle of the draft but just prior to
the proverbial 50ard line of the 2025
NFL draft.
>> Wilfield I know you got another mock
draft coming up. Do you want to tease
that at all? I don't want you to give
anything away but you know this is what
we live and breathe on here in the
spring.
>> Yeah pass catcher will be one of the
themes. Actually a two round mock draft.
So, a pass catcher and but that there
will certainly be a note in there that
this could all change if AJ Brown is
eventually shipped to New England. The
delicate balance that you know Elliot
Wolf and Mike Vrabel are dealing with is
that you know there's no way to agree to
a deal that's contingent upon getting
done after June 1st. Like the NFL does
not allow that. You could have an
agreement in principle but it can't be
fully executed. So, uh, for any number
of reasons, a deal that you think is
done on March 19th may not be done once
June 2nd rolls around. So, you almost
have to go into this draft, uh, counting
on receiver as a need, address it if you
so desire. Keep in mind that AJ Brown
could become available, but I'm sure the
Patriots and Eagles have have had plenty
of conversations about how realistic
that could be. and we still have five
weeks until the NFL draft. So, even more
time for them to kind of flesh out the
parameters of a potential deal. A pass
catcher will be a need there for the
Patriots. I would note that uh they're
in that sweet spot at the back end of
the first round as well that teams will
call, right? It's not just teams that
maybe want to get up into the back end
of the first round for a quarterback.
And this does feel like one of those
years where we could see a team move up
for Ty Simpson out of Alabama. I think
he will make it into the 20s. But the
other thing that I would note is teams
do want that fifth year of contract
control. Uh the Carolina Panthers moved
up just a couple of years ago from 33 to
32 to get Xavier Legette, the wide
receiver out of South Carolina. And and
and it could be that they wanted the
fifth year of contract control. That's
the only motivation. It also could be
that if you know a team is convinced
that Seattle or whoever might be picking
at 32 is going to take who they really
want to at the top of the second round
then they could be motivated to jump
ahead uh and get to number 31. So
tradeback is something that I think
almost every team likes to do especially
in a draft class like this. So wouldn't
surprise me if the Patriots are
proactive and finding suitors that could
come up to number 31 overall just given
the fact that I think the caliber of
player between 31 and 37 40 is pretty
similar even in a draft in which the
Patriots have at least right now the
third most picks of any team in the NFL.
>> A lot of uncertainty when you're down
there at the bottom of the first round.
Makes it a little bit more exciting I
think. Of course they trade out. Could
be a long night, but we'll let that
happen. Feel, thank you so much for
taking the time and uh we'll continue to
look out for your mock drafts and uh see
what comes about in April.
>> Thanks, dudes. Appreciate you having me
on.